<folder>

<foldername>logdist</foldername><filename>Contents</filename>

<h1 id="logdist/Contents">Probability distribution package</h1>

<p>This is a package (implemented as a class of static methods) that allows
you to set up and use some basic univariate distributions. These can be
used as priors in the <link id="model/estimate"><tt>estimate</tt></link> and <link id="poster/arwm"><tt>arwm</tt></link> functions.</p>

<p>The logdist package is called to create function handles that have
several different modes of use. The primary use is to compute values that
are proportional to the log of the respective density. In addition, the
function handles also give you access to extra information (such as the
the proper p.d.f., the name, mean, std dev, mode, and stuctural
parameters of the distribution), and to a random number generator from
the respective distribution.</p>

<h3>Getting function handles for univariate distributions</h3>

<ul><li><link id="logdist/normal"><tt>normal</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of normal distribution.</li>
<li><link id="logdist/lognormal"><tt>lognormal</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of log-normal distribution.</li>
<li><link id="logdist/beta"><tt>beta</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of beta distribution.</li>
<li><link id="logdist/gamma"><tt>gamma</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of gamma distribution.</li>
<li><link id="logdist/invgamma"><tt>invgamma</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of inv-gamma distribution.</li>
<li><link id="logdist/uniform"><tt>uniform</tt></link>&nbsp;&ndash;&nbsp;Create function proportional to log of uniform distribution.</li></ul>

<h3>Calling the logdist function handles</h3>

<p>The function handles <tt>F</tt> created by the logdist package functions can be
called the following ways:</p>

<ul><li>Get a value proportional to the log-density of the respective
distribution at a particular point (this call is used within the
<link id="poster/Contents">posterior simulator</link>):
<pre>   y = F(x)
</pre></li>
<li>Get the density of the respective distribution at a particular point:
<pre>   y = F(x,'pdf')
</pre></li>
<li>Get the characteristics of the distribution -- mean, std deviation,
mode, and information (the inverse of the second derivative of the log
density):
<pre>   m = F([],'mean')
   s = F([],'std')
   o = F([],'mode')
   i = F([],'info')
</pre></li>
<li>Get the underlying <tt>'structural'</tt> parameters of the respective
distribution:
<pre>   a = F([],'a')
   b = F([],'b')
</pre></li>
<li>Get the name of the distribution (the names correspond to the function
names, i.e. can be either of <tt>'normal'</tt>, <tt>'lognormal'</tt>, <tt>'beta'</tt>,
<tt>'gamma'</tt>, <tt>'invgamma'</tt>, <tt>'uniform'</tt>):
<pre>   name = F([],'name')
</pre></li>
<li>Draw a vector or matrix of random numbers from the distribution;
drawing from beta, gamma, and inverse gamma requires the Statistics
Toolbox:
<pre>   a = F([],'draw',1,1000);
</pre>
<pre>   size(a)
   ans =     
          1        10000
</pre></li></ul>

<h3>Getting on-line help on logdist functions</h3>
<pre>   help logdist
   help logdist/function_name
</pre>

</folder>